Brother Cornelius Russell Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Brother Cornelius Russell Papers
1900 – 2009
NPKMC-223-158
8.5 linear feet
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Bro. Cornelius Russell
This collection contains materials from Brother Russell's time in the US Army during World War II and his time as a Novitate and Marist Brother. John J. Russell was born on February 29, 1920 to Joseph Russell and Genevieve Toner in Manhattan, New York. John was drafted into the Air Force dring World War II. At the end of John’s Army career in 1946, he heeded his late calling to join the Order of Marist Brothers. Brother Cornelius was a humble person who lived by the Marist Principle to “do good quietly.”
Collection Overview
The Brother Cornelius Russell Papers contains correspondence to his family from his three year tour in the United States Army during World War II and from his Novitiate years as a Marist Brother. This collection also includes photos of his family and friends, diplomas from various schools, awards Brother Cornelius received throughout his life, and his World War II uniform.
The Brother Cornelius Russell Papers was donated to Marist College Archives and Special Collections by the family of Brother Cornelius Russell in 2009.
Historical Note
John J. Russell was born on February 29, 1920 to Joseph Russell and Genevieve Toner in Manhattan, New York. He was the oldest of three siblings; he had two younger sisters, Genevieve and Mary Russell. Because he was color blind John was not able to enlist in the United States Army in the early stages of World War II. When the war escalated John was drafted and chose to go into the Air Force Weather Squadron. His duties included observing the weather to ensure it was clear for army planes, and making sure they were able to take off and land safely at their destinations; without his signature on the departure form, no plane could leave the hanger. His major assignment was in Tindouf, Algeria at the weather station. John advanced in the ranks throughout his three year tour to Technical Sergeant.
At the end of John’s Army career in 1946, he heeded his late calling to join the Order of Marist Brothers. John’s first experience with the Brothers was during his elementary school days when they acted as his teachers. He also had connections to this order through his Aunt Tess, who was a Sister in a related order. After serving as a Novitiate for two years John received the Marist Habit and also during this time, graduated from Marian College (now Marist College) with a degree in history in 1950. In 1953 John made his final vows to join the Marist Brotherhood for life, and was renamed Brother J. Cornelius Russell.
Brother Cornelius was a humble person who lived by the Marist Principle to “do good quietly.” Before he returned to Marist College, Brother Cornelius taught at other Marist Brother Schools, including schools in the Bronx and Briarwood in New York, Lawrence, Massachusetts, and Augusta, Georgia. During this time, he received an MBA, from Columbia University. In 1962 Brother Cornelius was brought to Marist College to incorporate a business major to help widen the school’s curriculum and to draw in more prospective students. He was the first full-time business faculty member and first business department chairman at Marist College. In 1964 President Foy appointed him Controller, a position he held for several years. As the Controller Brother Cornelius had the responsibility of overseeing Marist College’s financial planning. On May 20th, 1995 Brother Cornelius was given the President’s Award by President Murray for his diligence while at Marist College and after his retirement. During his retirement he was also able to devote more of himself to the Marist Brotherhood and on March 3, 1996 he was given Pope John Paul II Apostolic Blessing. Brother Cornelius’s long and excellent teaching record was recognized on October 10th, 2003 when he was named one of Marist’s Heritage Professors.
Brother Cornelius was a vibrant, but humble person who left his mark on not only Marist College, but on the lives and hearts of many other people he met throughout his travels.
There are no restrictions on this collection
These records are arranged into four series: 1. Textual Material, had six suberies, subseries 1.3 has two subseries, and subseries 1.5 had secen subseries, 2. Photographic Material, 3. Textile Material, 4. Personal Materials
Series are arranged by subject.
- 1. Textual Material, 1942 - 2007; 1; Boxes: 1 - 6 Folders: 1 - 79
  Series contains WWII textual material, WWII correspondence, oversized materials, Marist Brotherhood correspondence, variety textual material, amd awards.
  Subject
  - Subseries 1.1: WWII Textual material, 1942 - 1943; 1.1; Box: 1 Folders: 1 - 27
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 April 7- 1942 April, 30 (Folder 1, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 May 1- 1942- May 31 (Folder 2, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 June1-1942- June 29 (Folder 3, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 July 1- 1942 July 31 (Folder 4, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 August 1- 1942 August 29 (Folder 5, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 September1- 1942 September 30 (Folder 6, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 October 2 -1942 October 25 1942 (Folder 7, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 November 5- 1942 November 29 (Folder 8, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1942 December 1- 1942 December 31 (Folder 9, Box 1)
    - Letter to John Russell from his friend Bob giving John and updates on his life and to thank John for birthday wishes., 1942 February 26 (Folder 10, Box 1)
    - Letter to John Russell from Father S. Pishul, inviting John to Dinner before his departure overseas., 1942 April 7 (Folder 11, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 January 1-1943 January 30 (Folder 12, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 February 1 -1943 February 28 (Folder 13, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 March 2-1943March 30 (Folder 14, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943April 1-1943April 30 (Folder 15, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 May 2-1943 May 31 (Folder 16, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 June 2- 1943 June 30 (Folder 17, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 July 2 - 1943 July 30 (Folder 18, Box 1)
    - Letters to his immediate family detailing his schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to his mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943August 1- 1943 August 31 (Folder 19, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 September 1 -1943 September 30 (Folder 20, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 October 2-1943 October 31 (Folder 21, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 November 1 -1943 November 16 (Folder 22, Box 1)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1943 December 1 - 1943 December 30 (Folder 23, Box 1)
    - Letter to Jack (aka John) from Val, giving details of what has been happening overseas in the African areas where Val is stationed., 1943 April 11 (Folder 24, Box 1)
    - Detailed typed documents detailing the promotion of John Russell from private to Staff Sergeant and second promotion to Technical Sergeant, 1943May 1; 1943 June 1 (Folder 25, Box 1)
    - Letter to John Russell’s father from Captain Jurell T. Baily stating return of John Russell’s letters, and boasting of John Russell’s virtue as a weatherman., 1943 July 4 (Folder 26, Box 1)
    - Letter to Mrs. Russell from Orpha D. Wissler, Protestant Chaplain and Joseph J Walsh Catholic Chaplain assuring Mrs. Russell that John Russell arrived in North Africa safely, and may not be in tough foe a few days because the group is only at a temporary Army Post., 1943 November 30 (Folder 27, Box 1)
  - Subseries 1.2: World War II Correspondences, 1944 - 1945; 1.2; Box: 2 Folders: 28 - 49
    - V-MAIL to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 January 1, - 1944 January 6 (Folder 28, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 February 1, -1944 February 28 (Folder 29, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 March 4, - 1944March 30 (Folder 30, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 April 2, - 1944 April 30 (Folder 31, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944May 3,- 1944 May 30 (Folder 32, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 June 1, - 1944 June 25 (Folder 33, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 September 2, -1944 September 25 (Folder 34, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., October 5, 1944- October 20, 1944 (Folder 35, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 November 2, - 1944 November 29 (Folder 36, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1944 December 2, - 1944 December 31 (Folder 37, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity, 1945 January 2-1945 January 28 (Folder 38, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 February 1, - 1945 February 28 (Folder 39, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 March 2, - 1945 March 31 (Folder 40, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945April 2, - 1945April 30 (Folder 41, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 May 15, - 1945 May 29 (Folder 42, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 June 12, - 1945 June 27 (Folder 43, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 July 3, - 1945 July 30 (Folder 44, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 August 1, - 1945 August 31 (Folder 45, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 September 2, - 1945 September 21 (Folder 46, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 October 3, -1945 October 29 (Folder 47, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 November 4, - 1945 November 20 (Folder 48, Box 2)
    - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., 1945 December 1, - 1945 December 12 (Folder 49, Box 2)
  - Subseries 1.3: Oversized Material, 1944 - 1958; 1.3; Box: 3 Folders: 50 - 51
    Series contains diplomas and preservation photocopies of damaged correspondences.
    - Subseries 1.3.1: Diplomas, 1950 - 1956; 1.3.1; Box: 3 Folder: 50
      - Diplomas from the United state Army Air Force Technical school (enlisted Weather Forecaster); Marian College (BA: Cum Lauda); Columbia University in New York City (Master of Arts), 1943 April 17, 1950 September 15, 1956 December 19 (Folder 50, Box 3)
    - Subseries 1.3.2: Preservation Photocopies of Damaged Correspondences, 1944 - 1958; 1.3.2; Box: 3 Folder: 51
      - Letters to immediate family detailing schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity. Original correspondences attached to photocopy., 1944 September 23, 1958 November 16 (Folder 51, Box 3)
  - Subseries 1.4: Correspondences while in the Marist Brotherhood 1950 - 1959, 1.4; Box: 4 Folders: 52 - 46
    - Letter to father from John Russell for Father’s Day from Marian College that is run by the Marist brothers. Thanking his father for all that he had done for him throughout his life. Letter also gives updates on how the semester and classes are going., 1950 June 18 (Folder 52, Box 4)
    - Letter from the United States Treasury Department in New York, NY to Genevieve from Brother Cornelius Russell. Giving his sister Birthday wishes and reminiscing of child hood with his sister., 1950 June 29 (Folder 53, Box 4)
    - Letter to Brother Cornelius from fellow Marist Brother. Letter contains sympathy regarding the death of Brother Cornelius’s father., 1953 October 24 (Folder 54, Box 4)
    - Letter to John from Aunt Helen. Letter contains updates on moving from one Chapel to another that is closer to family in New York. Details continue about religious life and concern over health., 1957 July 16 (Folder 55, Box 4)
    - Correspondences to his family while training for the Marist Brotherhood in Paris with other novices from around the world. Letters contain information such as day to day activity and updates on personal health., 1958 October - 1959 January 4 (Folder 56, Box 4)
  - Subseries 1.5: Variety textual Material, 1942 - 2007; 1.5; Boxes: 5 Folders: 57 - 76
    Series contains correspondence, miscellaneous material, apologia, Gregory Bridge Club Notes, papers, envelopes, and a journal
    - Subseries 1.5.1: Correspondences with Missing Pages, 1942 - 1945; 1.5.1; Box: 5 Folder: 57
      - World War II correspondences that have missing pages that contain details his schedule, how he is settling in and if there will be any changes to his mailing address when moving to different stations and day to day activity., Circa 1942 - 1945 (Foldaer 57, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.2: Miscellaneous Material, 1942 - 2007; 1.5.2; Box: 5 Folders: 58 - 70
      - contains a weather region map drawn my John Russell, Circa 1942 (Folder 58, Box 5)
      - An Early edition of the Marist College News paper “ Reynard’s Record” that mentions brother Cornelius coming to Marist College, 1961, February 14 (Folder 59, Box 5)
      - A list of Names (possibly army friends), Circa 1943 (Folder 60, Box 5)
      - A brief outline of the lives and death of Brother Cornelius family, Circa 1960 (Folder 61, Box 5)
      - A letter Brother Cornelius wrote to a Michelle about having a birthday on leap year and its difficulties, Circa 1990 (Folder 62, Box 5)
      - A birthday card from the Marist Brothers, 2007 (Folder 63, Box 5)
      - the back of a notebook with football players clearly labeled “Fordham” and “Notre Dame”, Circa 1945 (Folder 64, Box 5)
      - A typed letter to the office of President Elect Barack Obama from the archbishop of Chicago, Francis Cardinal George., 2008 (Folder 65, Box 5)
      - Unknown Hand written Correspondence, Circa 1950 (Folder 66, Box 5)
      - Passport of Mary A. Russell (Contains Picture), Issued 1975 July 15 (Folder 67, Box 5)
      - Prayer Book, 2007 (Folder 68, Box 5)
      - Funeral Program for Brother Cornelius, 2009 (Folder 69, Box 5)
      - News letter from the Cabrini Nursing Home containing an article about Brother Cornelius, 2007 (Folder 70, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.3: Apologia, 2001 - 2004; 1.5.3; Box: 5 Folder: 71
      - Friend and Classmate of Brother Cornelius; Brother Joe’s Apologia consist of a detailed rendition of his life and an explanation on why Brother Joe chose the Marist brotherhood and devoted himself to God., Begun: 2001 August, Completed: 2004 August (Folder 71, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.4: Gregory Bridge Club Notes, 1971 - 1977; 1.5.4; Box: 5 Folder: 72
      - The Gregory Bridge Club Meeting Notes taken by the secretary of the club; Brother Cornelius., Circa 1971-1977 (Folder 72, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.5: Papers, 1.5.5; Box: 5 Folders: 73 - 74
      - Genealogical analysis of “The Russell’s” using censuses, death, birth, and marriage records to trace an ancestral line., Circa 1861- 1906 (Folder 73, Box 5)
      - Veterans History project for the Library of Congress. John Russell is interviews about his years in World War II by second cousin., 2006 October 2 (Folder 74, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.6: Envelopes, 1942 - 2007; 1.5.6; Box: 5 Folder: 75
      - Envelopes that do not correspond to correspondences, Circa 1942 -2007 (Folder 75, Box 5)
    - Subseries 1.5.7: Journal, 1972 - 1975; 1.5.7; Box: 5 Folder: 76
      - A small journal kept by brother Cornelius of two trips taken in Europe with his sisters, May and Genevieve., First trip: 1972 May 28- June 18, Second trip: 1975 August 1- August 27 (Folder 76, Box 5)
  - Subseries 1.6: Awards, 1955 - 2003; 1.6; Box: 6 Folders: 77 - 79
    - Marist College Presidents Award, 1955 May 20 (Folder 77, Box 6)
    - Pope John Paul II Apostolic Blessing of Brother Cornelius Russell, 1996 March 3 (Folder 78, Box 6)
    - Heritage Professor Title to Brother Cornelius Russell, 2003 October 10 (Folder 79, Box 6)
- 2. Photographic Material, 1900 - 2009; 2; Boxes: 7 Folders: 80 - 95
  Series contains photographic materials
  - Early years of Brother Cornelius and immediate family, 1900- 1947 (Folder 80, Box 7)
  - United States Army Photos: Brother Cornelius in full uniform; and Army friends., 1940- 1943 (Folder 81, Box 7)
  - Marist brother Photos: Novitiate years; Official Marist Brother., 1948- 1958 (Folder 82, Box 7)
  - Later Family Photos: Brother Cornelius later in life with Sisters., 1983- 1991 (Folder 83, Box 7)
  - Papal Blessing Ceremony Photos: Cornelius receiving the Papal Blessing., 1988 March (Folder 84, Box 7)
  - Commencement Ceremony Photos: Brother Cornelius being recognized for his work at Marist College before he retires. Receiving Presidents Award., Circa 1995 (Folder 85, Box 7)
  - Graduation Ceremony Photos: Brother Cornelius taking part in graduation ceremony., Circa 1996 (Folder 86, Box 7)
  - Marist College Campus photos: Brother Cornelius and his sisters visit Holy Trinity Church at Marist College., 1994 December - 1995 August (Folder 87, Box 7)
  - Spring Lake Photos: Brother Cornelius and family vacationing at Spring Lake in New Jersey., Circa 1995 (Folder 88, Box 7)
  - Jubilee Photos: Brother Cornelius, family and other guests at spring Jubilee., Circa 1997 (Folder 89, Box 7)
  - Brother Cornelius and other Marist Brothers at Nursing home and other outings., 1993- 2000 (Folder 90, Box 7)
  - Heritage Professors Photos: Brother Cornelius and other recipients receiving the Heritage Professor Award., 2003 October 10 (Folder 91, Box 7)